<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="REED.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="REED.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>


<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:base="tei/records/" xml:id="london" xml:lang="eng"> 
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            
            <title type="main">Inns of Court</title>

            
            <funder><orgName>Andrew W. Mellon Foundation, New York, United States of America</orgName></funder>
            <funder><orgName>CANARIE</orgName></funder> 
            
            <funder><orgName>British Academy, London, UK</orgName></funder>
            <funder><orgName>Jackman Foundation, Toronto, Canada</orgName></funder>            
            <funder><orgName>National Endowment for the Humanities, Washington, DC, United States of
               America</orgName></funder>
            <funder><orgName>Social Sciences and Humanities Research Council, Ottawa,
               Canada</orgName></funder>
            
		 <editor resp="print"><persName xml:id="AHN1">Alan H. Nelson</persName></editor>
		 <editor resp="print"><persName>John R. Elliott, Jr.</persName></editor>
            
            <respStmt>
               <persName xml:id="CB">Carolyn Black</persName>
               <orgName>Records of Early English Drama (REED)</orgName>
               <resp>Project Manager</resp>
            </respStmt>
            
            <respStmt>
               <persName>John Bradley</persName>
               <resp>NHPRC-Mellon Project Team Member</resp>
            </respStmt>
            
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Susan Brown</persName> 
               <orgName>University of Guelph</orgName>
               <resp>NHPRC-Mellon Project Team Member</resp>
            </respStmt>
            
            <respStmt>
               <persName xml:id="KC">Kathy Chung</persName>
               <orgName>Records of Early English Drama (REED)</orgName>
               <resp>REED Research Associate, NHPRC-Mellon Project Consultant</resp>
            </respStmt>
            
            <respStmt>
               <persName>William Cooke</persName>
               <orgName>Records of Early English Drama (REED)</orgName>
               <resp>English Glossarian</resp>
            </respStmt>
            
            <respStmt>
               <persName xml:id="JC">James Cummings</persName>
               <orgName>Newcastle University</orgName>
               <resp>Records of Early English Drama (REED) Executive Board</resp>
               <resp>NHPRC-Mellon Project Team Member</resp>
               <resp>TEI Schema Designer, Technical Consultant</resp>
            </respStmt>
            
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Matthew Davies</persName>
               <orgName>University of London, Birkbeck College</orgName> <!-- confirm -->
               <resp>Records of Early English Drama (REED) Executive Board</resp>
               <resp>NHPRC-Mellon Project Team Member</resp>
            </respStmt>
            
            <respStmt>
               <persName xml:id="PG">Patrick Gregory</persName>
               <orgName>Records of Early English Drama (REED)</orgName>
               <resp>Associate Editor</resp> <!-- confirm -->
               <resp>Paleographer, Translator</resp> <!-- confirm -->
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Tanya Hagen</persName>
               <orgName>Records of Early English Drama (REED)</orgName>
               <resp>Bibliographer, NHPRC-Mellon Project Consultant</resp>
            </respStmt>
            
            <respStmt>
               <persName xml:id="JAKA1">Diane K. Jakacki</persName>
               <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
               <resp>Records of Early English Drama (REED) Executive Board</resp>
               <resp>Principal Investigator, NHPRC-Mellon Digital Edition Publishing Cooperatives Planning Grant</resp>
            </respStmt>
            
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Alexandra F. Johnston</persName>
               <orgName>Records of Early English Drama (REED)</orgName>
               <resp>REED Founder and Senior Consultant</resp>
            </respStmt>
            
            <respStmt>
               <persName>David Kathman</persName>
               <resp>NHPRC-Mellon Project Team Member</resp>
            </respStmt>
            
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Sally-Beth MacLean</persName>
               <orgName>Records of Early English Drama (REED)</orgName>
               <resp>Principal Investigator, SSHRC grant; Director of Research and General Editor</resp>
               <resp>NHPRC-Mellon Project Team Member</resp>
            </respStmt>

            <respStmt>
               <persName>Maureen Maclean</persName>
               <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
               <resp>REED London research assistant, 2018</resp>
            </respStmt>
            
            <respStmt>
               <persName xml:id="KM">Kimberley Martin</persName>
               <orgName>University of Guelph</orgName>
               <resp>NHPRC-Mellon Project Consultant</resp>
            </respStmt>
            
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Christopher Matusiak</persName>
               <orgName>Ithaca College</orgName>
               <resp>NHPRC-Mellon Project Team Member</resp>
            </respStmt>
            
            <respStmt>
               <persName xml:id="JN">Jamie Norrish</persName>
               <resp>Programmer, EATS developer, NHPRC-Mellon Project Consultant</resp>
            </respStmt>
            
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Dorothy Porter</persName>
               <orgName>University of Pennsylvania</orgName>
               <resp>NHPRC-Mellon Project Team Member</resp>
            </respStmt>
            
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Arleane Ralph</persName>
               <orgName>Records of Early English Drama (REED)</orgName>
               <resp>Paleographer</resp>
            </respStmt>
            
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Suzanne Westfall</persName>
               <orgName>Lafayette College</orgName>
               <resp>Records of Early English Drama (REED) Executive Board Member</resp>
               <resp>NHPRC-Mellon Project Team Member</resp>
            </respStmt>
            
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Abigail Ann Young</persName>
               <orgName>Records of Early English Drama (REED)</orgName>
               <resp>Latin Glossarian</resp>
            </respStmt>
            
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>Print version, published <date when-iso="2010">2010</date>. Electronic edition, anticipated publication <date when-iso="2018">2018</date></edition>
         </editionStmt>
         
         <publicationStmt>
            <authority><orgName>Records of Early English Drama (REED)</orgName>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>University of Toronto</addrLine>
                  <addrLine>170 St George Street, Suite 810</addrLine>
                  <addrLine>Toronto, Ontario, Canada</addrLine>
                  <addrLine>M5R 2M8</addrLine>
               </address>
            </authority>
            
            <publisher>D.S. Brewer, Cambridge, an imprint of Boydell &amp; Brewer Ltd./Boydell &amp; Brewer Ltd.</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Rochester, NY</pubPlace>
            <date>2010</date>
            <idno type="other">978-1-84384-259-0</idno>
            
            <availability>
               <p>Copyright <orgName>Records of Early English Drama (REED)</orgName>,
                  <date>2017</date></p>
               <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/">Distributed under a
                  Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-SA
                  4.0) licence.</licence>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Records of Early English Drama</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>This publication constitutes a remediation of the printed Inns of Court collection. Information on original sources for transcriptions can be accessed via the Document Descriptions.</p>
            <p>For a full list of REED collections, editors, executive board members, and staff, please visit http://reed.utoronto.ca/people</p>       
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      
      <encodingDesc>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="taxon" matchPattern="([A-Za-z0-9_-]+)"
               replacementPattern="../taxonomy.xml#$1">
               <p>Private URIs using the <code>taxon</code> prefix are pointers to entities in the
                  taxonomy.xml file. For example, <code>taxon:church</code> dereferences to
                  <code>taxonomy.xml#church</code>.</p>
            </prefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="gloss" matchPattern="([A-Za-z0-9_-]+)"
               replacementPattern="../glossary.xml#$1">
               <p>Private URIs using the <code>gloss</code> prefix are pointers to entities in the
                  glossary.xml file. For example, <code>gloss:histrio-1</code> dereferences to
                  <code>glossary.xml#histrio-1</code>.</p>
            </prefixDef>
         </listPrefixDef>
         
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Records of Early English Drama (REED) is an international scholarly project that is
               establishing for the first time the context from which the drama of Shakespeare and his
               contemporaries grew. Founded in 1976, REED has worked since then to locate, transcribe,
               and edit historical documents containing evidence of drama, secular music, and other
               communal entertainment and ceremony from the Middle Ages until 1642, when the Puritans
               closed the London theatres.</p>
         </projectDesc>
      </encodingDesc>
      
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">English</language>
            <language ident="lat">Latin</language>
            <language ident="fra">Anglo-French</language>
         </langUsage>
         <settingDesc>
            <place>
               <placeName>London</placeName> 
            </place>
         </settingDesc>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <!-- Add new major milestone changes to top -->
         <change when="2018-04-23" who="#KC">start adding records to file</change>
         <change when="2018-02-03" who="#JAKA1">created document</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   
   <text ana="taxon:inner_temple" type="record">
      <body xml:lang="eng">
         <head>
            <date from-iso="1610" to-iso="1611" cert="medium">1610-11</date> <!-- KC: might need to confirm with Carolyn about this tagging. This is the date range of the record accounting year.  The actual date of the record would be 10 Feb 1610 to them and 10 Feb 1611 to us modern people because new year started from 25 March at the time. -->
            <seg ana="taxon:RLITPB2" corresp="taxon:RPCIC p. 145">RLITPB2</seg></head>
         <div type="transcription">
            <head>f 99<supplied>(10 February)</supplied></head>
            <pb n="99" type="folio"/> 
            
            <gap reason="omitted"/>
            
            <ab>
               Whereas, <note type="marginal" place="margin_left">Private Comons taken awaie in Christmas</note> great disorders doe growe in this howse and greate losse and
               detryment to many yonge gent<ex>lemen</ex> fellowes of the same, by reason of
               kepinge pryvate Com<ex>m</ex>ons in Chr<ex>is</ex>tmas It is at this p<ex>ar</ex>liam<ex>en</ex>t ordered
               That from henceforth there shalbee noe pryvate Com<ex>m</ex>ons kept in this
               howse in the tyme of Chr<ex>istmas</ex>, but that the Comons of the howse shall
               henceforth bee contynued dureing Chr<ex>istmas</ex> tyme as in other tymes of the
               yeare w<ex>i</ex>thout any dyceinge or other disorder. Neither shall there bee any
               Lorde or breaking vpp of any mans Chamber vppon payne that every p<ex>e</ex>rson
               w<ex>hi</ex>ch hereaft<ex>er</ex> shall attempt any such thinge shall incurre the danger and
               penaltie of the form<ex>er</ex> orders in that behalf heretofore made./
            </ab>
            
            <ab> 
               And <note type="marginal" place="margin_left"> Noe playes one festyvall days.</note>for that great disorder &amp; scurrilytie is brought into this howse by lewde
               &amp; lasciuious playes. It is likewise ordered in this p<ex>ar</ex>liam<ex>en</ex>t that from
               henceforth there shalbe no more playes in this howse either vpon the ffeast
               of all S<ex>ain</ex>ct<ex>es</ex> or Candlemas day, but the same from henceforth to bee vtterly
               taken awaie and abolyshed
            </ab>
            
               <gap reason="omitted"/>

         </div>
      </body>
   </text>           
   
   <text ana="taxon:inner_temple" type="record">
      <body xml:lang="eng">
         <head>
            <date from-iso="1611" to-iso="1612" cert="medium">1611-12</date>  
            <seg ana="taxon:RLITPB2" corresp="taxon:RPCIC p. 146-7">RLITPB2</seg>
         </head>
         
         <div type="transcription">
            <head>f 105v<supplied>(24 November)</supplied></head> <!-- KC: actual record date is 24 Nov 1611 -->
            <pb n="105v" type="folio"/> 
            
            <gap reason="omitted"/>
            
            <ab>
               Where[of] <note type="marginal" place="margin_left">The order for layinge downe of playes repealed.</note>of late yeares vpon the two festivall dayes of All S<ex>ain</ex>t<ex>es</ex> and Candlemasse playes haue beene vsed after dinne<ex>r</ex> for recreacion w<ex>hi</ex>ch haue lately beene layd downe by order in Parliament It is now ordered that the same order shall henceforth stand repealed.
            </ab>
            
             <gap reason="omitted"/>
               
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>    
   

   <text ana="taxon:inner_temple" type="record">
      <body xml:lang="eng">
         <head>
            <date from-iso="1612" to-iso="1613" cert="medium">1612-13</date>
            <seg ana="taxon:RLITP2" corresp="taxon:RLPIC1 pp. 151-2">RLITPB2</seg></head>
         <div type="transcription">
            <head>f 112v<supplied>(4 May)</supplied></head>  <!-- KC: this makes actual record date 4 May 1613 -->
            <pb n="112v" type="folio"/>
            <gap reason="omitted"/>
            <ab>
               fforasmuche it is found by experience That the vtterbarresters, of this howse, as alsoe other gentl<ex>emen</ex> vnder the barre doe vsually vnder hand &amp; secretlie contrarie to the Statut<ex>es</ex> &amp; orders of this howse, make sale of theire Chambers, for great som<ex>m</ex>es of money, and convert the same to theire owne privat vse to the great p<ex>re</ex>iudice and state of this howse And for that contrariewise It is seen from the experience of other howses of Courte, that throughe sale made of Chambers by the governors of such howse muche benefitt and proffitte hath growne to the gen<ex>er</ex>al state of the same: with furderance and due content of the Student<ex>es</ex> there, And forasmuche as this howse att this p<ex>re</ex>sent is muche indebted by reason of the late showe and sport<ex>es</ex> made by the gentl<ex>emen</ex> of this howse before his highnes att whitehall Amountinge in Charges vnto the howse (over and besides the stocke of this howse,) not soe litle as xij<hi rend="superscript">C</hi> li. which requires somme extraordynarie and unwonted course of supply, but noe meanes as yet discerned therein soe fittinge as suche husbandlye course of admittanc<ex>es</ex>, Be it therefore enacted att this p<ex>re</ex>sent ^<add place="above">parliament</add> that hencefourth all admittanc<ex>es</ex> into anye Chamber or Chambers of this howse in possession or Reverc<ex>i</ex>on (other then Bench<ex>er</ex>s Chambers priviledged by acte of p<ex>ar</ex>liam<ex>en</ex>t) shalbe made from tyme to tyme by acte of p<ex>ar</ex>liam<ex>en</ex>t, and not by the Th<ex>reasour</ex>er of this ^<add place="above">howse</add> allone as heretofore haue ben, and that all admittances otherwise had or made shalbe <del><damage/></del> voyde, And it is furder enacted that vppon everye suche admittance by acte of p<ex>ar</ex>liament the p<ex>ar</ex>tie or p<ex>ar</ex>ties to be admitted shall over and above the former vsuall &amp; accustomed fine for an admittance paye vnto the Th<ex>reasour</ex>er of this howse suche furder som<ex>m</ex>e or som<ex>m</ex>es of money for such Chamber or Chambers as shalbe then assessed and sett downe for suche admittanc<ex>es</ex> as the worth of the chamber or chambers will in the iudgement of such p<ex>ar</ex>liament afford to be sold betweene p<ex>ar</ex>tie and p<ex>ar</ex>tie, Nevertheles it is alsoe furder enacted that everye p<ex>er</ex>son soe admitted and payinge suche som<ex>m</ex>e of money shall att any tyme after vppon his surrender of suche his interest in suche Chamber or Chambers, wherein he shall stand soe admitted as aforesaid, haue repaide backe vnto him by the Th<ex>reasour</ex>er of this howse three full p<ex>ar</ex>t<ex>es</ex> in foure p<ex>ar</ex>t<ex>es</ex> devided of the wholl fine or som<ex>m</ex>e of money which he shall haue soe formerlie paid and disbursed as aforesaid, And this acte to be sufficient warrant and discharge to suche Th<ex>reasour</ex>er for the tyme beinge in that behaulf,: Provided alwayes that this acte or anie thinge therein contayned shall not extend to anye Chamber, Chambers, or Rowmes, wherein anye of this Socyetie haue anie graunt by anye acte of p<ex>ar</ex>liament, but that everye suche p<ex>er</ex>son and p<ex>er</ex>sons theire executors and assignes shall haue Contynue and enioye there said Chambers and Romes, whereof and wherein they stand soe admitted with all priviledg<ex>es</ex> and benefitt<ex>es</ex> in as lardge and beneficiall manner to all purposes as the same were graunted vnto them or to anie other vnder whome they Clayme the same by force of anye acte of p<ex>ar</ex>liament heretofore made anye thinge in this acte to the contrarie notwithstandinge/
            </ab>
         </div>
         
         <div type="editorial">  
            <ab>The phrase ‘late showe and sport<ex>es</ex>’ (p 151, l.41) refers to Beaumont’s <hi rend="italic">Masque of the Inner Temple and Gray’s Inn</hi>, performed in the Banqueting House, Whitehall, on 20 February 1612/13, following the marriage of Princess Elizabeth and the count palatine. The figure ‘xij<hi rend="superscript">C</hi> li.’(£1200), if doubled to allow for Gray’s Inn’s share, tallies roughly with the total of £2255 8s 11d calculated by Orbison (ed), <hi rend="italic">Collections</hi> 12, p 7, to have been the cost of George Chapman’s masque presented by the Middle Temple and Lincoln’s Inn for the same occasion.</ab>
         </div>
               
         <div type="transcription">
            <head>f 120<supplied>(10 July)</supplied></head>
            <pb n="120" type="folio"/>
            <gap reason="omitted"/>
            <ab>At this Parliament yt is ordered that Mr Lumley the drap<ex>er</ex> shallbe paid fower pownd<ex>es</ex> twelve shilling<ex>es</ex> &amp; sixe pence, for scarlett ymployed for the Marshall at the Maske</ab>
            <gap reason="omitted"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
  
   <!-- 1633-34 record -->
      <text ana="taxon:inner_temple" type="record">
      <body xml:lang="eng">
         <head>
            <date from-iso="1633" to-iso="1634" cert="medium">1633-4</date>
            <seg ana="taxon:RLITPB2" corresp="taxon:RPCIC p. 140-3">RLITPB2</seg>
         </head>
         
         <div type="transcription">
            <head>f 219-19v<supplied>(12 November)</supplied></head>
            <pb n="219-19v" type="folio"/> 
            
            <gap reason="omitted"/>
            
            <ab>
               Whereas <note type="marginal" place="margin_left">Ayde Rolle for
                  the Masque</note>there having bene no representacion of any Maske or other Shewe
   before the Kings Maiestie by the fower Inns of Court or any of them sythence
   his Highnesse accesse vnto the Crowne, a Consultacion hath bene latelie had
   by the severall Benchers in theire severall howses touching the same Wherevpon
   it is vnanimousk..l agreed by them, that a Maske shall bee ioyntk..l presented
   in this next Christmas before his Maiestie, att the equall charges of the saik.l
   fower howses. It is therefore nowe ordered and enacted att this parliament
   That for the raysing and leavying of moneys towardes the defraying of the said
   Charge everie ffellowe of this howse shall bee taxed to paye as followeth, vizt./
   Everie Bencher of this howse to paye the summe of five powndes.
   Ev
   erie Vtter Barrister of this howse being seaven yeares standing of the Barr
   or vpward fiftie shillinges./
   Everie Vtter Barrister of this howse which is vnder seaven yeares standing of
   the Barr fortie shillinges
   Everie Gentleman vnder the Barr who hath bene in Commons within one
   yeare last past or is nowe in Commons or shall bee in Commons within one
   yeare next ensuinge to paye twentie shillinges And euerie such Gentleman
   vnder the Barr who hath a Chamber in the howse to paye twentie shillinges
   although he hath not bene in Commons within one year last past as aforesaid.
   And that such as are hereafter named who have or keepe the severall Offices
   hereafter mencioned within this howse shall paye (over and besides the summes
   aforesaid) for and in respect of theire said severall Offices the severall summes
   following, That is to saye/
   Richard Brownlowe Esquier for his Office of Cheiffe Prothonotary of the
   Common pleas five powndes./
   Robert Henly and Samuell Wightwick Esquiers for the Kinges Bench Office
   ten powndes
   Thomas ffanshawe Esquier for the Crowne Office six powndes thirteene
   shillinges and fower pence
   Mr Hugh Audley for the Office of Wardes and Liveries ten powndes
   Mr William Blage for his Office of Cyrographer Ten powndes
   Mr William Rolfe for his Office of Clark of the Warrantes six powndes
   thirteene shillinges and fower pence./ |
   Mr Richard Barringer for his Office of Philozer three powndes six shillinges
   and eight pence
   Mr Matthewe Cradock for his Office of Clark of Assizes fortie shillinges
   Mr ffrancis Williamson for his Office of Clark of Assizes fortie shillinges
  
   Mr Humfrey Streete for his Office of Auditor three powndes six shillinges
   and eight pence
   And it is further ordered that the Cheiffe Butler shall make a Rolle of
   the names of all such ffellowes of this howse as are chargeable with the
   paymentes aforesaid and collect the same forthwith, and from tyme to tyme
   deliver such summes of money as he shall collect vpon the said Rolle vnto
   the handes of Mr Willis one of the Benchers of this howse, whoe togeather
   with Mr Cesar of the Barr and Mr Pollard of the Masters Commons are
   intreated to take care of the disbursing of the said summes of money towardes
   the preparacion aforesaid.
            </ab>
            <gap reason="omitted"/>
       </div>
   
       <div type="transcription">
          <head>f 222v<supplied>(9 February)</supplied></head>
          <pb n="222" type="folio"/> 
 
               <gap reason="omitted"/>
    <ab>           
       fforasmuch <note type="marginal" place="margin_left">Order for master
          Treasourer to disburse moneyes towards the Maske</note>
       as the moneyes taxed and imposed vpon all the Gentlemen of
   this Societie by a former Act of parliament of the 12th of November last
   towardes the defraying of the charge of the masque latelie presented before
   his Maiestie, will come farre short of soe greate a summe as will bee occasioned
   thereby, as nowe appeared by the relacion of mr Willis att this parliament,
   who hath bene imployed and trusted in that [busines] service. And forasmuch
   as master Treasourer of this howse hath alreadie furnished the said mr Willis
   with somme moneyes out of the Stock of this howse for that purpose, and
   there is present occasion for the disbursing of more towardes that service. It
   is therefore ordered att this parliament That the said master Treasourer may
   deliver vnto the handes of the said mr Willis out of the stock of the howse
   such further moneys as hee shall haue occasion to expende and laye out about
   the same busines, vntill some further course shall bee taken for the raysing of
   soe greate a summe And that this present Act shall bee a sufficient warrant
   and discharge to the said master Treasourer as well for all such moneyes as hee
   hath alreadie deliverd or shall hereafter deliver to the said mr Willis for the
   purpose aforesaid. The said master Treasourer taking a Receipt or Receipts
   from the said mr Willis for the same./
    </ab>
          <gap reason="omitted"/>
       </div>
          
          <div type="transcription">
             <head>f 223<supplied>(27 April)</supplied></head>
             <pb n="223" type="folio"/> 
             
             <gap reason="omitted"/>
<ab>
   Whereas <note type="marginal" place="margin_left"> Reference touching the
      Masque</note>by an act of parliament made the twelft daye of November last
   it was ordered that a Rolle shoulde bee made for the raysing of moneyes
   towardes the defraying of the charge of the masque therein mencioned and
   sythence presented before his Maiestie, and that the Cheiffe Butler of this
   howse shoulde collect the moneys due vpon the same Rolle and from tyme
   to tyme deliver the same soe by him collected vnto the handes of Mr Willis
   one of the Benchers of this howse for the disbursing thereof in such manner
   as by the said Act appeareth. And whereas alsoe by another Act of parliament
   made the nynth daye of ffebruary last, it was ordered (That whereas Master
   Treasourer of this howse had then formerlie furnished the said Mr Willis with
   somme moneyes out of the Stock of the howse for that purpose, and that
   there was then present occasion for disbursing of more towardes that service)
   That the said Master Treasourer might deliver vnto the handes of the said
   Mr Willis out of the Stock of the howse such further moneyes as hee should
   have occasion to expende about the same busines, taking a receipte or receiptes
   from the said Mr Willis for the same And whereas the said Mr Willis hath
   receaved not onlie severall summes of money collected vpon the said Rolle
   from the handes of the Cheiffe Butler of this howse but alsoe the summe of
   six hundred twentie and six powndes of the said Master Treasourer out of the
   Stock of this howse by vertue of the said last recited act of parliament to
   bee imployed towardes the charge of the said Masque. It is therefore att this
   parliament desired that Mr Trotman Mr Bulstrod and Mr ffarer three of
   the Benchers of this howse will aswell consider of all the said Mr Willis his
   receiptes and disbursementes already had and made about the said Masque,
   and howe and in what manner the same have bene imployed as alsoe what
   other moneyes they shall conceave necessarie to bee further raysed for the
   discharge thereof yf it shall appeare vnto them, there is not sufficient in the
   handes of the said Mr Willis to defraye the same. And that they will report
   theire opinions to the Boarde touching the same with what convenient speede
   they maye to the ende such further course may bee taken therein as shall
   bee thought fitt./
                  </ab>
             <gap reason="omitted"/>
          </div>
         
             <div type="transcription">
                <head>f 224v<supplied>(22 June)</supplied></head>
                <pb n="224" type="folio"/> 
                
                <gap reason="omitted"/>
<ab>
   Whereas by an Act of parliament made the 27th daye of Aprill last, It was
   [ordered] LdesiredJ that Mr Trotman Mr Bulstrod and Mr ffarrar three of
   the Benchers of this howse woulde aswell consider of the Receiptes and
   disbursementes before that tyme had and made by Mr Willis one other of
   the Benchers of this howse, about the Masque latelie presented before his
   Maiestie, and howe the same had bene imployed as alsoe what other moneyes
   they shoulde conceave necessarie to bee further raysed for the discharge
   thereof, yf it should appeare vnto them there was not sufficient in the handes
   of the said Mr Willis to defraye the same. Nowe vpon the Report of the said
   Committees that there is not sufficient in the handes of the said Mr Willis
   to defraye the said Charge, and that hee will have occasion to disburse one
   hundred powndes more att the least over and aboue his former Receiptes It
   
   <note type="marginal" place="margin_left">Order for Master Treasurer to disburse 
      more money towardes the masque</note>
   is therevpon att this parliament ordered that Master Treasurer of this howse
   may deliver vnto the said Mr Willis out of the Stock of the howse such
   further summes of money as there shall bee necessarie occasion to bee
   disbursed about the defraying of the said charge, taking a Receipte or Receiptes
   from the said Mr Willis for the same. And it is ordered that this present Act
   shall bee a sufficient warrant and discharge to the said Master Treasurer in
   that behalfe./
</ab>
                <gap reason="omitted"/>
             </div>
          </body>
      </text>
</TEI>
