<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="REED.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="REED.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:base="tei/records/" xml:id="london" xml:lang="eng">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Inns of Court</title>
            <funder><orgName>Andrew W. Mellon Foundation, New York, United States of America</orgName></funder>
            <funder><orgName>CANARIE</orgName></funder>
            <funder><orgName>British Academy, London, UK</orgName></funder>
            <funder><orgName>Jackman Foundation, Toronto, Canada</orgName></funder>
            <funder><orgName>National Endowment for the Humanities, Washington, DC, United States of America</orgName></funder>
            <funder><orgName>Social Sciences and Humanities Research Council, Ottawa, Canada</orgName></funder>
            <editor resp="print"><persName xml:id="AHN1">Alan H. Nelson</persName></editor>
            <editor resp="print"><persName>John R. Elliott, Jr.</persName></editor>
            <respStmt>
               <persName xml:id="CB">Carolyn Black</persName>
               <orgName>Records of Early English Drama (REED)</orgName>
               <resp>Project Manager</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>John Bradley</persName>
               <resp>NHPRC-Mellon Project Team Member</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Susan Brown</persName>
               <orgName>University of Guelph</orgName>
               <resp>NHPRC-Mellon Project Team Member</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName xml:id="KC">Kathy Chung</persName>
               <orgName>Records of Early English Drama (REED)</orgName>
               <resp>REED Research Associate, NHPRC-Mellon Project Consultant</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>William Cooke</persName>
               <orgName>Records of Early English Drama (REED)</orgName>
               <resp>English Glossarian</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName xml:id="JC">James Cummings</persName>
               <orgName>Newcastle University</orgName>
               <resp>Records of Early English Drama (REED) Executive Board</resp>
               <resp>NHPRC-Mellon Project Team Member</resp>
               <resp>TEI Schema Designer, Technical Consultant</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Matthew Davies</persName>
               <orgName>University of London, Birkbeck College</orgName>
               <!-- confirm -->
               <resp>Records of Early English Drama (REED) Executive Board</resp>
               <resp>NHPRC-Mellon Project Team Member</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName xml:id="PG">Patrick Gregory</persName>
               <orgName>Records of Early English Drama (REED)</orgName>
               <resp>Associate Editor</resp>
               <!-- confirm -->
               <resp>Paleographer, Translator</resp>
               <!-- confirm -->
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Tanya Hagen</persName>
               <orgName>Records of Early English Drama (REED)</orgName>
               <resp>Bibliographer, NHPRC-Mellon Project Consultant</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName xml:id="JAKA1">Diane K. Jakacki</persName>
               <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
               <resp>Records of Early English Drama (REED) Executive Board</resp>
               <resp>Principal Investigator, NHPRC-Mellon Digital Edition Publishing Cooperatives Planning Grant</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Alexandra F. Johnston</persName>
               <orgName>Records of Early English Drama (REED)</orgName>
               <resp>REED Founder and Senior Consultant</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>David Kathman</persName>
               <resp>NHPRC-Mellon Project Team Member</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Sally-Beth MacLean</persName>
               <orgName>Records of Early English Drama (REED)</orgName>
               <resp>Principal Investigator, SSHRC grant; Director of Research and General Editor</resp>
               <resp>NHPRC-Mellon Project Team Member</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Maureen Maclean</persName>
               <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
               <resp>REED London research assistant, 2018</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName xml:id="KM">Kimberley Martin</persName>
               <orgName>University of Guelph</orgName>
               <resp>NHPRC-Mellon Project Consultant</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Christopher Matusiak</persName>
               <orgName>Ithaca College</orgName>
               <resp>NHPRC-Mellon Project Team Member</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName xml:id="JN">Jamie Norrish</persName>
               <resp>Programmer, EATS developer, NHPRC-Mellon Project Consultant</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Dorothy Porter</persName>
               <orgName>University of Pennsylvania</orgName>
               <resp>NHPRC-Mellon Project Team Member</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Arleane Ralph</persName>
               <orgName>Records of Early English Drama (REED)</orgName>
               <resp>Paleographer</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Suzanne Westfall</persName>
               <orgName>Lafayette College</orgName>
               <resp>Records of Early English Drama (REED) Executive Board Member</resp>
               <resp>NHPRC-Mellon Project Team Member</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <persName>Abigail Ann Young</persName>
               <orgName>Records of Early English Drama (REED)</orgName>
               <resp>Latin Glossarian</resp>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>Print version, published <date when-iso="2010">2010</date>. Electronic edition, anticipated publication <date when-iso="2018">2018</date></edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <authority><orgName>Records of Early English Drama (REED)</orgName>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>University of Toronto</addrLine>
                  <addrLine>170 St George Street, Suite 810</addrLine>
                  <addrLine>Toronto, Ontario, Canada</addrLine>
                  <addrLine>M5R 2M8</addrLine>
               </address>
            </authority>
            <publisher>D.S. Brewer, Cambridge, an imprint of Boydell &amp; Brewer Ltd./Boydell &amp; Brewer Ltd.</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Rochester, NY</pubPlace>
            <date>2010</date>
            <idno type="other">978-1-84384-259-0</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>Copyright <orgName>Records of Early English Drama (REED)</orgName>, <date>2017</date></p>
               <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/">Distributed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-SA 4.0)
                  licence.</licence>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Records of Early English Drama</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>This publication constitutes a remediation of the printed Inns of Court collection. Information on original sources for transcriptions can be accessed via the Document Descriptions.</p>
            <p>For a full list of REED collections, editors, executive board members, and staff, please visit http://reed.utoronto.ca/people</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="taxon" matchPattern="([A-Za-z0-9_-]+)" replacementPattern="../taxonomy.xml#$1">
               <p>Private URIs using the <code>taxon</code> prefix are pointers to entities in the taxonomy.xml file. For example, <code>taxon:church</code> dereferences to
                     <code>taxonomy.xml#church</code>.</p>
            </prefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="gloss" matchPattern="([A-Za-z0-9_-]+)" replacementPattern="../glossary.xml#$1">
               <p>Private URIs using the <code>gloss</code> prefix are pointers to entities in the glossary.xml file. For example, <code>gloss:histrio-1</code> dereferences to
                     <code>glossary.xml#histrio-1</code>.</p>
            </prefixDef>
         </listPrefixDef>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Records of Early English Drama (REED) is an international scholarly project that is establishing for the first time the context from which the drama of Shakespeare and his
               contemporaries grew. Founded in 1976, REED has worked since then to locate, transcribe, and edit historical documents containing evidence of drama, secular music, and other communal
               entertainment and ceremony from the Middle Ages until 1642, when the Puritans closed the London theatres.</p>
         </projectDesc>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">English</language>
            <language ident="lat">Latin</language>
            <language ident="fra">Anglo-French</language>
         </langUsage>
         <settingDesc>
            <place>
               <placeName>London</placeName>
            </place>
         </settingDesc>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <!-- Add new major milestone changes to top -->
         <change when="2018-02-03" who="#JAKA1">created document</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text ana="taxon:inner_temple" type="record">
      <body xml:lang="eng">
         <head>
            <date when-iso="1612" cert="medium">1612</date>
            <seg ana="taxon:RLITP2" corresp="taxon:RLPIC1 pp. 151-2">RLITPB2</seg></head>
         <div type="transcription">
            <head>f 112v<supplied>(4 May)</supplied></head>
            <pb n="f 112v" type="folio" />
            <gap reason="omitted" />
            <ab> fforasmuche it is found by experience That the vtterbarresters, of this howse, as alsoe other gentl<ex>emen</ex> vnder the barre doe vsually vnder hand &amp; secretlie contrarie to
               the Statut<ex>es</ex> &amp; orders of this howse, make sale of theire Chambers, for great som<ex>m</ex>es of money, and convert the same to theire owne privat vse to the great
                  p<ex>re</ex>iudice and state of this howse And for that contrariewise It is seen from the experience of other howses of Courte, that throughe sale made of Chambers by the governors
               of such howse muche benefitt and proffitte hath growne to the gen<ex>er</ex>al state of the same: with furderance and due content of the Student<ex>es</ex> there, And forasmuche as this
               howse att this p<ex>re</ex>sent is muche indebted by reason of the late showe and sport<ex>es</ex> made by the gentl<ex>emen</ex> of this howse before his highnes att whitehall
               Amountinge in Charges vnto the howse (over and besides the stocke of this howse,) not soe litle as xij<hi rend="superscript">C</hi> li. which requires somme extraordynarie and unwonted
               course of supply, but noe meanes as yet<note type="foot">for no meanes are as yet</note> discerned therein soe fittinge as suche husbandlye course of admittanc<ex>es</ex>, Be it therefore enacted att this p<ex>re</ex>sent ^<add
                  place="above">parliament</add> that hencefourth all admittanc<ex>es</ex> into anye Chamber or Chambers of this howse in possession or Reverc<ex>i</ex>on (other then Bench<ex>er</ex>s
               Chambers priviledged by acte of p<ex>ar</ex>liam<ex>en</ex>t) shalbe made from tyme to tyme by acte of p<ex>ar</ex>liam<ex>en</ex>t, and not by the Th<ex>reasour</ex>er of this ^<add
                  place="above">howse</add> allone as heretofore haue ben, and that all admittances otherwise had or made shalbe <del><damage /></del> voyde, And it is furder enacted that vppon everye
               suche admittance by acte of p<ex>ar</ex>liament the p<ex>ar</ex>tie or p<ex>ar</ex>ties to be admitted shall over and above the former vsuall &amp; accustomed fine for an admittance
               paye vnto the Th<ex>reasour</ex>er of this howse suche furder som<ex>m</ex>e or som<ex>m</ex>es of money for such Chamber or Chambers as shalbe then assessed and sett downe for suche
                  admittanc<ex>es</ex> as the worth of the chamber or chambers will in the iudgement of such p<ex>ar</ex>liament afford to be sold betweene p<ex>ar</ex>tie and p<ex>ar</ex>tie,
               Nevertheles it is alsoe furder enacted that everye p<ex>er</ex>son soe admitted and payinge suche som<ex>m</ex>e of money shall att any tyme after vppon his surrender of suche his
               interest in suche Chamber or Chambers, wherein he shall stand soe admitted as aforesaid, haue repaide backe vnto him by the Th<ex>reasour</ex>er of this howse three full
                  p<ex>ar</ex>t<ex>es</ex> in foure p<ex>ar</ex>t<ex>es</ex> devided of the wholl fine or som<ex>m</ex>e of money which he shall haue soe formerlie paid and disbursed as aforesaid, And
               this acte to be sufficient warrant and discharge to suche Th<ex>reasour</ex>er for the tyme beinge in that behaulf,: Provided alwayes that this acte or anie thinge therein contayned
               shall not extend to anye Chamber, Chambers, or Rowmes, wherein anye of this Socyetie haue anie graunt by anye acte of p<ex>ar</ex>liament, but that everye suche p<ex>er</ex>son and
                  p<ex>er</ex>sons theire executors and assignes shall haue Contynue and enioye there said Chambers and Romes, whereof and wherein they stand soe admitted with all priviledg<ex>es</ex>
               and benefitt<ex>es</ex> in as lardge and beneficiall manner to all purposes as the same were graunted vnto them or to anie other vnder whome they Clayme the same by force of anye acte
               of p<ex>ar</ex>liament heretofore made anye thinge in this acte to the contrarie notwithstandinge/ </ab>
         </div>
         <note type="editorial">
            <ab>The phrase ‘late showe and sport<ex>es</ex>’ (p 151, l.41) refers to Beaumont’s <hi rend="italic">Masque of the Inner Temple and Gray’s Inn</hi>, performed in the Banqueting House,
               Whitehall, on 20 February 1612/13, following the marriage of Princess Elizabeth and the count palatine. The figure ‘xij<hi rend="superscript">C</hi> li.’(£1200), if doubled to allow for
               Gray’s Inn’s share, tallies roughly with the total of £2255 8s 11d calculated by Orbison (ed), <hi rend="italic">Collections</hi> 12, p 7, to have been the cost of George Chapman’s
               masque presented by the Middle Temple and Lincoln’s Inn for the same occasion.</ab>
         </note>
         <div type="transcription">
            <head>f 120<supplied>(10 July)</supplied></head>
            <pb n="f 120" type="folio" />
            <gap reason="omitted" />
            <ab>At this Parliament yt is ordered that Mr Lumley the drap<ex>er</ex> shallbe paid fower pownd<ex>es</ex> twelve shilling<ex>es</ex> &amp; sixe pence, for scarlett ymployed for the
               Marshall at the Maske</ab>
            <gap reason="omitted" />
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
