<oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/"
xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
  <dc:title>Inner Temple Christmas Accounts, 1633-34</dc:title>
  <dc:subject>Theater--England--London--History--17th century</dc:subject>
  <dc:subject></dc:subject>
  <dc:subject></dc:subject>
  <dc:description>&quot;The Christmas account of William York for a single first week of the Christmas commons of 1633 fills a lacuna in the Christmas Account Book. A second account, kept by John Williams, another 1633 Christmas steward, was identified by archivists at the Derbyshire Record Office in 1988 (D258/Box 30/8), but as it yields no entries of REED interest further details are omitted here. A third account was kept by Henry Kemp for the third and fourth weeks of Christmas in this same year. All three documents are associated with the ‘Gell papers,’ documents from 1610–48 originally gathered by Thomas Gell of the Inner Temple (admitted 28 May 1612). Henry Chandos-Pole (1829–1902), second son of Edward Sacheverell Chandos-Pole, inherited Hopton Hall and estate from Philip Gell, formally taking the name Gell in 1865. The papers are now allocated permanently to the Derbyshire Record Office. Searches for the third docu- ment in the Derbyshire Record Office in 1988 and again in 1991 were unsuccessful.&quot;</dc:description>
  <dc:contributor>Inner Temple</dc:contributor>
  <dc:type>Text</dc:type>
  <dc:type>Born Digital</dc:type>
  <dc:type>born digital</dc:type>
  <dc:type>Record</dc:type>
  <dc:type>Archival material</dc:type>
  <dc:type>Performance</dc:type>
  <dc:format>electronic resource</dc:format>
  <dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
  <dc:identifier>reed:d68eea79-1f5e-4577-bc42-b2b8e8dc2f4e</dc:identifier>
  <dc:language>English</dc:language>
  <dc:coverage>London</dc:coverage>
  <dc:coverage>1601-1700</dc:coverage>
  <dc:rights>Use of this public-domain resource is governed by the &lt;a
            rel=&quot;license&quot; href=&quot;http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/&quot;
            target=&quot;blank&quot;&gt;Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International
            License&lt;/a&gt;.</dc:rights>
</oai_dc:dc>
