<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Title</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Information about the source</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <p><title><hi rend="Bold">Bulstrode Whitelocke’s ‘Annals’</hi></title> BL: Additional MS
            53726</p>
         <p> f 89v col 1–f 94v col 2*</p>
         <gap reason="Omitted"/>

         <p>About Allhollantide, seuerall of the principall members of the Societies of the fower
               <orgName>Innes of Court</orgName>, amongst whom, some were seruants to the
               <persName>king</persName>, had a designe that the <orgName>Innes of Court</orgName>
            should present their seruice to the <persName>King</persName> &amp;
               <persName>Queen</persName> &amp; testify their affections to them, by the outward
            &amp; splendid visible [of] testimony, of a <name type="entertainment">Royall
               Masque</name> of all the <orgName>4. societies</orgName> ioyning togither, to be by
            them brought to the <orgName>Court</orgName>, as an expression of their loue &amp; duety
            to their <persName>M<ex>aies</ex>tyes</persName>.</p>

         <p>This was hinted att in the <orgName>Court</orgName> &amp; by them intimated to the
            Chiefes of those societies, that it would be well taken from them, &amp; some held it
            the more seasonable, bicause this action would mainest<note type="foot"><hi
                  rend="italic">with abbreviation mark over</hi> n <hi rend="italic">(?); for</hi>
                  mani<ex>f</ex>est</note> the difference of their opinion from <persName>Mr
               Prynnes</persName> new learning, &amp; serue to confute his Histriomastix against
            enterludes.</p>

         <p>This designe tooke well, with all the <orgName>Innes of Court</orgName>, especially the
            younger sort of them, &amp; in order to putt it in execution, the Benchers of<note
               type="foot"><hi rend="italic">start of col 2 on f 89v</hi></note> each society mett,
            &amp; agreed, to haue this solemnity performed, in the noblest &amp; most stately manner
            that could be inuented.</p>

         <p>The better to effect this, it was resolued, in each house to choose two of their
            Members, whom they should iudge fittest, for such a buisnes, to be a Committee, by ioint
            assistance to carry on that affayre.</p>

         <p>In the <orgName>middle Temple</orgName> were chosen of this Committee, <persName>Mr
               Edward Hyde</persName> &amp; <!-- INNS OF COURT 1633-4                    271 -->
            <persName>Whitelocke</persName>, for the <orgName>Inner Temple</orgName>
            <persName>S<ex>i</ex>r Edward Herbert</persName>, and <persName>Mr Selden</persName>.
            for <orgName>Lincolnes Inne</orgName>
            <persName>M<ex>aste</ex>r Atturney Noy</persName>, &amp; <persName>Mr
            Gerling</persName>, &amp; for <orgName>Greyes Inne</orgName>, <persName>S<ex>i</ex>r
               Iohn Fynch</persName> &amp; Mr(<ex>blank</ex>)</p>

         <p>This Committee being impowred by the Benchers of each society, mett togither, &amp; out
            of their own number made seuerall subcommittees, one subcommittee to take care, of the
            poeticall part of the buisnes, another for the seuerall properties of the Masquers &amp;
            Antimas | quers, &amp; other actors, another was for the dauncing, &amp; to me in
            particular was committed, the whole care &amp; charge of all the Musicke for this <name
               type="Entertainment">Great Masque</name>.</p>

         <p>The buisnes being thus distributed, each subcommittee had their meetings, &amp; carryed
            on their buisnes, committed to their care, &amp; had monyes prouided, by an equall
            proportion, by the Gouernors of each society, who were not sparing, in that most
            materiall part, of euery designe &amp; action.</p>

         <p>I made choyce of <persName>Mr Symon Iue</persName>, an honest &amp; able Musitian, of
            excellent skill in his Art, &amp; of <persName>Mr Lawes</persName><note type="foot"><hi
                  rend="italic">ie, William Lawes</hi></note>, to Compose the aiers, lessons &amp;
            songs for the <name type="Entertainment">Masque</name>, &amp; to be the masters of all
            the musicke under me.</p>

         <p>I also made choice of 4. of the most excellent musitians of the <orgName>Queens
               Chappell</orgName>, <persName>M<ex>o</ex>n<ex>sieu</ex>r La Mare</persName>,
                  <persName>M<ex>o</ex>n<ex>sieu</ex>r Du Vale</persName>,
                  <persName>M<ex>o</ex>n<ex>sieu</ex>r Robert</persName>, &amp;
                  <persName>M<ex>o</ex>n<ex>sieu</ex>r Mari</persName>, and of diuers others of
            forrein nations, who were most eminent in their Art, not in<note type="foot"><hi
                  rend="italic">start of col 2 on f 90</hi></note> the least neglecting any of my
            own Countrymen, whose knowledge in Musicke, rendred them usefull in this action, to
            beare their parts in the Musicke, which I resolued if I could, to haue so performed, as
            might excell any musicke, that euer before this time had bin in England.</p>

         <p>Herein I kept my purpose, &amp; for the better preparation &amp; practise of the
            Musicke, &amp; that I myselfe might take the better care, &amp; be present with them, I
            caused the meetings of all the Musitians, to be frequent att my house in
               <placeName>Salisbury Court</placeName>, and there I haue had togither att one time,
            of English, French, Italian, Germans, &amp; other Masters of Musicke, fourty Lutes,
            besides other Instruments, &amp; voyces of the most excellent musitians in consort.</p>

         <p>The rest of the subcommittees prepared all things in readyness according to their
            seuerall charges, &amp; the Grandees, <persName>M<ex>aste</ex>r Atturney
               Generall</persName>, <persName>Noy</persName>, <persName>S<ex>i</ex>r Iohn
               Fynch</persName>, <persName>S<ex>i</ex>r Edward Herbert</persName>, <persName>Mr
               Selden</persName>, &amp; all the rest of the Committees, tooke great paynes, &amp;
            neglected no | meetings for the management of this great business, of the masque which
            they knew would be acceptable to their Master &amp; Mistress &amp; to all the court.</p>

         <p>The time for presenting of this <name type="Entertainment">masque</name> att
               <placeName>Whitehall</placeName>, was agreed to be on <name type="Holiday">Candlemas
               night</name> to end <name type="Holiday">Christmas</name>, &amp; the seuerall parts
            of it being brought neer to a readiness for action, <persName>Hyde</persName> and
               <persName>Whitelocke</persName>, were sent by the Committee, to the <persName>Lord
               Chamberlein</persName>, the <persName>Earle of Pembroke &amp; Montgomery</persName>,
            &amp; to <persName>S<ex>i</ex>r Henry Vane</persName> the Comtroller of the kings house
            to aduise with them, <!--272        INNS OF COURT 1633-4--> &amp; to take order, about
            the Sceane, &amp; other matters relating to the <name type="Entertainment"
            >Masque</name>, &amp; about preparing things in the <placeName>Banquetting
               house</placeName>, in order therto, &amp; being all mett there for that purpose to
            view to<note type="foot"><hi rend="italic">for</hi>the<hi rend="italic">(?)</hi></note>
            places &amp; to order the matters.</p>

         <p>In the debate about them it happened, that there was a difference of opinion between
               <persName>Sir Henry Vane</persName> &amp; <persName>Whitelocke</persName>,
                  <persName>S<ex>i</ex>r Henry</persName> who had as great pride as parts, and a
            scornfull slighting way of expressinge himselfe, expected according to the name of his
            office, to be<note type="foot"><hi rend="italic">start of col 2 on f 90v</hi></note>
            Comptroller of all other mens iudgements, &amp; to haue all things done according to his
            own, &amp; not otherwise, and appeared to hold himselfe who was a great officer &amp; a
               <name type="occupation">priuy Counsellor</name>, to be undervalued, in a young <name
               type="occupation">Lawyers</name> difference of opinion, from his wisdome, &amp; not
            att first subscribing to it, and swearing in verbo Magistri if the Comptroller
            understood so much Latin</p>

         <p>I thought the Socieites whose seruant I was, &amp; in a buisnes acceptable to both their
                  <persName>[M<ex>aies</ex>tyes] M<ex>aies</ex>tyes</persName>, to be underualued by
                  <persName>S<ex>i</ex>r Henry Vanes</persName> not vouchsafing such conveniences
            &amp; accomodations, as were requisite, &amp; the place did afforde, for the presenting
            of their seruices to their <persName>M<ex>aies</ex>tyes</persName> att the
               <orgName>Court</orgName>.</p>

         <p>I was befittingly humble to the <name type="occupation">priuy Counsellor</name>, yett
            would not sneake, nor admit of inconveniences, to my Masters, especially uppon this
            occasion. <persName>Mr Hyde</persName> tooke in rowndly with me, &amp; att length by the
            | <persName>Lord Chamberleins</persName> authority &amp; perswasions interposed, all
            things were ordered according to our desires, &amp; we parted, seeming all to be very
            good friends.</p>

         <p>The <placeName>Gallery</placeName> behind the state att the end of the
               <placeName>banquetting house</placeName>, was reserved for the gentlemen of the
               <orgName>Innes of Court</orgName>, who should come thither to see their <name
               type="entertainment">masque</name> that there they might sitt togither, &amp; none
            else to be admitted with them into that place.</p>

         <p>The <name type="occupation">Dauncers</name>, <name type="occupation">Masquers
               Antimasquers</name>, &amp; <name type="occupation">Musitians</name> did before hand
            practise in the place, where they were to present the <name type="entertainment"
               >Masque</name> &amp; the sceanes were arteficially prepared, att the lower end of the
               <placeName>Banquetting house</placeName>, &amp; all things were in readyness.</p>

         <p>The <name type="occupation">Grand Masquers</name> were fower gentlemen of each
                  <orgName>Innes<note type="foot"><hi rend="italic">for</hi>Inne</note> of
               Court</orgName>, most suitable for their persons, dauncing, &amp; garbe<note
               type="foot"><hi rend="italic">for</hi>garbed</note> for that buisnes, &amp; it was
            ordered, that they<note type="foot"><hi rend="italic">start of col 2 on f 91</hi></note>
            should be drawne in <name type="object">fower riche Chariotts, 4. Masquers in each
               Chariot, by 6 horses in each Chariot</name>.</p>

         <p>Butt there grew a difference, about the order of their going, which of the
               <orgName>Innes of Court</orgName> should haue the first <name type="object"
               >Chariot</name>, &amp; so of the rest in their order, &amp; how the seuerall <name
               type="occupation">grand Masquers</name> should sitt, in the seueral <name
               type="object">Chariots</name>, who in the first or chiefest place, &amp; who in the
            second, third, and last place.</p>

         <!-- INNS OF COURT 1633-4                    273 -->

         <p>To satisfy this it was propounded by <persName>Wh<ex>itelocke</ex></persName> &amp;
            assented to by the Committee, that the <name type="object">Chariots</name> should be
            made, after the fashion of the Roman Tryumphant Chariots, &amp; being of an Ovall forme
            in the seats, there would be no difference of place in them.</p>

         <p>For the seuerall colours, &amp; for the precedence of the <name type="object"
               >Chariots</name>, it was agreed, that one of each house, of the Committee, should
            throwe the dice, &amp; as that happened, the society to be bound of which he that threw
            was a member. I threw the dice for the <orgName>Middle Temple</orgName>, &amp; by my
            cast, had the | place for the second <name type="object">Chariot</name>, and siluer
            &amp; blew for my colours, which colours, I haue euer since kept in my liueryes, &amp;
            uppon all solemne occasions.</p>

         <p><name type="holiday">Candlemas day</name> being come, All the <name type="occupation"
               >Masquers, Horsemen, Musitians, Dauncers, &amp; all that were actors</name> in this
            buisnes, according to order, mett att <placeName>Ely house</placeName> in
               <placeName>Holborne</placeName>, in the afternoone.</p>

         <p>There the whole Committee sate all day, to order all affayres, and when the Euening was
            come, all things being in full readyness, they began to sett forth, eueryone in their
            order, towards <placeName>Whitehall</placeName>, their way was directed thorough
               <placeName>Chancery lane</placeName>, and from thence through <placeName>Temple
               barre</placeName>, &amp; so the high way to <placeName>Whitehall</placeName> to the
               <orgName>Court</orgName>.</p>

         <p>The first that marched, were <name type="object">twenty footmen in scarlet liueryes,
               with siluer lace, each one hauing his sword by his side, a baton in one hand, &amp; a
               torch lighted in the other hand, these were the Marshalls men</name>, who cleered the
            streets, made way, &amp; were all about the <name type="occupation">Marshall</name>
               waiting<note type="foot"><hi rend="italic">start of col 2 on f 91v</hi></note> his
            commaunds.</p>

         <p>After them, &amp; sometimes in the midst of them came the <name type="occupation"
               >Marshall</name>, then <persName>Mr Darrell</persName>, afterwards knighted by the
               <persName>king</persName>, an extraordinary hansome, proper gentleman, one of
               <orgName>Lincolnes Inne</orgName>, &amp; was agreed uppon by the Committee for this
            seruice.</p>

         <p>He was mounted uppon one of the <name type="object"><persName>Kinge</persName><note
                  type="foot"><hi rend="italic">for</hi>kinges</note> best horses, and richest
               saddles</name>, and his owne habit was exceeding rich &amp; glorious, his
            horsemanship very gallant, &amp; besides his Marshalls men, he had <name type="object"
               >two Lacquayes, who carryed torches by him, &amp; a page, in liuery, that went by him
               carrying his cloake</name>.</p>

         <p>After him followed one hundred gentlemen of the <orgName>Innes of Court</orgName>, fiue
            &amp; twenty chosen out of each house, of the most proper &amp; hansome young gentlemen
            of the societies.</p>

         <p>Euery one of them was gallantly mounted, on the best horses, &amp; with the best
            furniture, that the <persName>Kings</persName> stable | &amp; the stables of all the
            Noblemen in Towne, would afforde &amp; they were forward on this occasion, to lend them
            to the <orgName>Innes of Court</orgName>.</p>

         <p>
            <name type="object">Euery one of these 100 gentlemen, were in very rich clothes,
                  scare<note type="foot"><hi rend="italic">for</hi>scarce</note> anything butt gould
               &amp; siluer lace, to be seen of them, &amp; each gentleman, had a Page
               <!--274        INNS OF COURT 1633–4 --> &amp; two Lacquays waiting on him, in his
               liuery, by his horse side, &amp; euery on had his sword, the Lacquayes carryed
               torches &amp; the page, the cloake of his Master</name>.</p>

         <p>The richness of their apparell &amp; furniture, glittering by the light of the multitude
            of torches attending on them, with the motion &amp; stirring of their mettled horses,
            &amp; they many &amp; various gay liueryes of their seruants, butt especially, the
            personall beauty &amp; gallantry of the hansome young gentlemen made the most glorious
            and splendid show, that euer was beheld in <placeName>England</placeName>.</p>

         <p>After the <name type="occupation">horsemen</name>, came the <name type="occupation"
               >Antimasquers</name>, &amp; as the <name type="occupation">horsemen</name> had their
            musicke, about<note type="foot"><hi rend="italic">start of col 2 on f 92</hi></note> a
            dozen of the best <name type="occupation">Trompets</name>, proper for them, &amp; in
            their liuery sounding before them so the <name type="entertainment">first
               Antimasque</name>, being of <name type="object">Cripples &amp; Beggars on
               horseback</name>, had their musicke of keys &amp; tonges, &amp; the like, snapping
            &amp; yett playing in a consort before them.</p>

         <p>These <name type="object">beggers were also mounted, butt on the poorest leanest
               iades</name>, that could be gotten out of the dust cartes, or elsewhere, &amp; the
            variety &amp; change from noble musicke, &amp; gallant horses as went before them, unto
            their proper musicke &amp; pittifull horses, made both of them the more pleasing.</p>

         <p>The habits &amp; properties, of these <name type="object">Cripples &amp; Beggars</name>,
            were most ingeniously fitted, (as of all the rest) by the Committees direction, wherin
            (as in the whole buisnes) <persName>M<ex>aste</ex>r Atturney Noy</persName>,
                  <persName>S<ex>i</ex>r John Fynch</persName>, <persName>S<ex>i</ex>r Edward
               Herbert</persName>, <persName>Mr Selden</persName>, those great &amp; eminent
            persons, as all the rest of the Committee, had often meetings, &amp; tooke extraordinary
            care &amp; paynes, in the ordering of this buisnes, &amp; it seemed a pleasure to
            them.</p>

         <p>After the <name type="entertainment">Beggars antimasque</name> came <name type="object"
               >men on Horsebacke play | ing uppon pipes, whistles, &amp; instruments, sounding
               notes like those of birds of all sorts, &amp; in excellent consort</name>, &amp; were
            followed by the <name type="entertainment">antimasque of Birds</name>.</p>

         <p>This was an <name type="object">Owle in an Iuy bush, with many seuerall sorts of other
               Birdes, in a Cluster about the Owle gazing as it were uppon her, these were little
               boyes, putt into Couers of the shapes of those birdes, rarely fitted, &amp; sitting
               on smalle horses, with footmen going by them, hauing all of them torches in
                  their<note type="foot"><hi rend="italic">for</hi>their hands</note> &amp; the
               footmen likewise had in the former <name type="entertainment"
            >antimaske</name></name>, &amp; heer were some besides to looke unto the children, &amp;
            this was very pleasant to the beholders. After this <name type="entertainment"
               >antimasque</name> came other <name type="occupation">musitians</name> on <name
               type="object">horsebacke playing uppon Baggepipes, Hornepipes</name>, &amp; such kind
            of Northerne musicke speaking the following antimaske of proiectors, to be of the Scotch
            &amp; Northern quarters, &amp; these (as all the rest,<note type="foot"><hi
                  rend="italic">closing parenthesis omitted</hi></note> had many <name type="object"
               >footemen with torches waiting on them</name>. first in this <name
               type="entertainment">Antimasque</name> rode <name type="object">a fellow uppon a
               little horse with a great Bitt in his mouth, &amp; uppon the mans head, was a Bitt,
               with Head stall &amp; raines, fastened, and signifyed<note type="foot"><hi
                     rend="italic">start of col 2 on f 92v</hi></note> a proiector</name>, who
            begged a Patent, that none in the <!-- INNS OF COURT 1633–4                    275-->
            kingdome, might ride their horses, butt with such Bitts, as they should buy of him.</p>

         <p>Then came another <name type="object">fellowe with a bunche of Carretts uppon his head,
               &amp; a Capon uppon his fist, describing a proiector</name>, who begged a Patent of
            Monopoly, as the first inuenter of the art, to feed Capons fatt with Carrets, &amp; that
            none butt himselfe, might make use of that inuention, &amp; haue the priuiledge for 14
            years, according to the Statute</p>

         <p>Seuerall other <name type="occupation">proiectors</name> were in like manner personated,
            in their <name type="entertainment">antimasque</name>, &amp; it pleased the spectators
            the more, because by it, an information was covertly giuen to the
               <persName>King</persName>, of the unfittness, &amp; ridiculousness of these <name
               type="occupation">proiects</name>, against the law, &amp; <persName>Atturney
               Noy</persName> who had most knowledge of them, had a great hand in this <name
               type="entertainment">Antimasque of the Proiectors</name>. |</p>

         <p>After this &amp; the rest of the <name type="entertainment">Antimasquers</name> were
            past, all which are not heer remembred, there came sixe of the <name type="object"
               >Chiefe Musitians on Horsebacke, uppon footclothes, &amp; in the Habits of Heathen
               [pr] priests, &amp; footmen carrying of torches by them</name>.</p>

         <p>After those <name type="occupation">Musitians</name> followed <name type="object">a
               large open Chariot, drawne with sixe braue horses, with large plumes of feathers, on
               their heads &amp; buttockes, the Coachman &amp; postilian, in rich antique liueryes,
               in the Chariot were about a dozen persons in seuerall habits of the Gods &amp;
               Goddesses, &amp; by them many footmen on all sides bearing torches</name>.</p>

         <p>After this <name type="object">Chariot followed sixe more of the Musitians on horsebacke
               with footclothes habited &amp; attended with torches, as the former were</name>.</p>

         <p> After them, came another <name type="object">large open Chariot, like the former,
               drawne with six gallant horses, with feathers liueryes &amp; torches as the other
               had. these Chariots were<note type="foot"><hi rend="italic">start of col 2 on f
                     93</hi></note> made purposely for this occasion, &amp; in this latter Chariot
               were about a dozen Musitians in like habit, butt all with some variety, &amp;
               distinction, as those in the first Chariot</name>.</p>

         <p>These going immediately, next before the <name type="object">Grand Masquers
               Chariots</name>, played uppon excellent &amp; lowde musicke, all the way as they
            went.</p>

         <p>After this Chariot came <name type="object">6 more musitians on footclothe horses,
               habited &amp; attended as the other</name>. Then came the first <name type="object"
               >chariot of the Grand Masquers, which was not so large as those that went before,
               butt most curiously framed, carued, &amp; painted, with exquisite art, &amp;
               purposely for this seruice &amp; occasion. The forme of it, was after that of the
               Roman Triumphant Chariots, as neer as could be gathered by some old prints &amp;
               pictures extant of them, the seats in it were made of an Ouall forme in the backe end
               of the Chariot, so that there was no precedence in them, &amp; the faces of all that
               sate in it, might be seen togither</name>.</p>

         <!-- 276       INNS OF COURT 1633-4 -->

         <p>The <name type="object">Colours of this first Chariot were, siluer &amp; crimson</name>,
            giuen by | the lott to <orgName>Grayes Inn</orgName>, (as I remember) the <name
               type="object">Chariot was all ouer painted richly with these colours, even the
               wheeles of it, most artificially layd on, &amp; the carued worke of it was as curious
               for that art, &amp; it made a stately show</name>.</p>

         <p>It was <name type="object">drawne with fower horses all on breast, &amp; they were
               couered to their heeles all ouer, with cloth of tissue, of the colours of Crimson
               &amp; siluer, huge plumes of red and white feathers on their heads &amp; buttockes,
               the Coachmans Cap and feather, his long Coate, &amp; his very whippe &amp; cushion,
               of the same stuffe &amp; colour</name>.</p>

         <p>In this Chariot sate, the <name type="object">4 Graund Maskers of <orgName>Grayes
                  Inne</orgName>, their habits, doublets, trunke hose &amp; cappes of most riche
               cloth of tissue, and wrought as thicke with siluer spangles as they could be placed,
               large white silke stockins up to their trunke hose, &amp; rich sprigges in their
               cappes</name>, themselues proper &amp; beautifull young gentlemen.</p>

         <p>On <name type="object">each side of the Chariot were fower footmen, in liueryes of the
               colour of the Chariot, carrying huge flambois in their hands, which with the torches
               gaue such a lustre, to the paintings, spangles &amp; <note type="foot"><hi
                     rend="italic">start of col 2 on f 93v</hi></note>; habits, that hardly any [th]
               thing could be inuented to appeare more glorious</name>.</p>

         <p>After this Chariot came <name type="occupation">sixe more Musitians</name>, on
            footclothes &amp; in habits like the former. These were followed by the <name
               type="object">second chariot, as the lot fell for the <orgName>Middle
                  Temple</orgName>, this differed not in any thing from the former, butt in colours
               only, which were of this Chariot, siluer &amp; blue, it was drawne by my Coach
               horses, &amp; driuen by my own Coachman, in the like lieuery of blue &amp; siluer,
               &amp; the Chariot &amp; horses couered &amp; decked with cloth of tissue of blue
               &amp; siluer, as the former was with siluer &amp; crimson</name>.</p>

         <p>In this <name type="object">second Chariot, were the fower Grand masquers of the
                  <orgName>Middle Temple</orgName>, in the same habits as the other Masquers were,
               &amp; with the like attendance torches &amp; flambois with the former</name>. After
            these, followed the <name type="object">third &amp; fowerth Chariots, &amp; sixe
               Musitians between each Chariot, habited on footcloth horses as before, | the
               Chariots, were all of the same make, &amp; alike carued &amp; painted, differing only
               in the Colours</name>, in the third Chariot rode the <persName>Grand
               Masquers</persName> of the <orgName>Inner Temple</orgName>, and in the fourth Chariot
            went those of <orgName>Lincolnes Inne</orgName>, according to the lot of each of
            them.</p>

         <p>The habits of the <persName>16 Graund Masquers</persName> were all the same their
            persons most hansome &amp; louely, the Equipage so full of state &amp; height of
            gallantrye, that it neuer was outdone by any representation mentioned in our former
            stories.</p>

         <p>The <name type="object">Torches &amp; flaming huge flambois, borne by the sides of each
               Chariot</name>, made it seem lightsome as att noon day, butt more glittering, &amp;
            gaue a full &amp; cleer light to all the streets &amp; windowes as they passed by.</p>

         <!-- INNS OF COURT 1633-4                    277 -->

         <p>The Marche was slowe, in regard of their great numbers, butt more interrupted by the
            Multitude of the spectators, in the streets, besides the windowes, &amp; they all seemed
            loth to part with so<note type="foot"><hi rend="italic">start of col 2 on f
               94</hi></note> glorious a spectacle.</p>

         <p>This gaue opportunity to <persName>Hyde</persName> &amp;
            <persName>Whitelocke</persName>, who usually were togither, to take a <name
               type="occupation">Coach</name>, &amp; by the other way, to gett before them to
               <persName>Whitehall</persName>, where they found the fayre <placeName>banquetting
               house</placeName>, so crowded with fayre Ladyes, glistering with their rich clothes,
            &amp; richer jewells, &amp; with lords &amp; gentlemen of great quality, that there was
            scarse roome for the <persName>King</persName> &amp; <persName>Queen</persName> to enter
            in. They saw that all thinges were in readiness there, &amp; the L<ex>or</ex>d
            Chamberlein carryed them up to the Chamber of the beautifull &amp; ingenious Countess of
            Caernaruon <persName>his daughter</persName>, whose company was no smalle pleasure &amp;
            refreshment.</p>

         <p>The <persName>King</persName> &amp; <persName>Queen</persName> stood att a Windowe,
            looking streight foward into the street, to see the <name type="entertainment"
               >Masque</name> come by, &amp; being delighted with the Noble brauery of it, they sent
            to the <name type="occupation">Marshall</name> to desire that the whole show, might
            fetch a turne about the <placeName>Tiltyeard</placeName>, that their
                  <persName>M<ex>aies</ex>tyes</persName> might haue a double view of them, which
            was done accordingly &amp; then they all alighted att White | hall gate, &amp; were
            conducted to seuerall roomes &amp; places, prepared for them.</p>

         <p>The <name type="occupation">Horsemen</name> of the <name type="entertainment"
               >Masque</name>, and other gentlemen of the <orgName>Innes of Court</orgName>, sate in
            the Gallery reserued for them, &amp; those of the Committee that were present, were with
            them, only <persName>Hyde</persName> &amp; <persName>Whitelocke</persName> were placed
            belowe among the Grandees, &amp; neare the Sceane, that they might be ready to giue
            their assistance, if there should be occasion, &amp; as an extraordinary fauour [th] to
            them att that time, &amp; in that presence.</p>

         <p>The <persName>King</persName> &amp; <persName>Queen</persName>, &amp; all their Noble
            traine, being come in, the <name type="entertainment">Masque</name> began, &amp; was
            incomparably performed, in the dauncing speeches, musicke, &amp; sceanes, the daunces,
            figures, properties, the voices, instruments, songs, aiers, composures, the words &amp;
            actions were all of them exact, &amp; none fayled in their parts of them, and the sceans
            were most curious &amp; costly.</p>

         <p>The <persName>Queen</persName> did the honor to some of the <name type="occupation"
               >Masquers</name> to daunce with them herselfe, &amp; to iudge them, as<note
               type="foot"><hi rend="italic">start of col 2 on f 94v</hi></note> good dauncers as
            euer she sawe, &amp; the great Ladyes were very free &amp; ciuill in dauncing with all
            the <name type="occupation">Masquers</name> as they were taken out by them.</p>

         <p>Thus they continued in their sports untill it was almost the morning, &amp; then the
                  <persName>K<ex>ing</ex></persName> &amp; <persName>Queen</persName>, retiring to
            their chamber, the <persName>Masquers</persName> &amp; <orgName>Innes of Court</orgName>
            gentlemen were brought to a <name type="entertainment">stately banquet</name>, &amp;
            after that was dispersed, euery one departed to their own quarters.</p>

         <p>Thus was this earthly pomp &amp; glory (if not vanity) soone past ouer &amp; gone, as if
            it had neuer bin, &amp; as all worldly gories<note type="foot"><hi rend="italic"
                  >for</hi>glories</note> are, but for a moment
            <!--278        INNS OF COURT 1633–4 --> Lett it therfore (my children) be your care, to
            slight these earthly glories, &amp; not to sett your affections on them, but to seeke
            after that eternall weight of glory, which will neuer passe away.</p>
         <gap reason="omitted"/>

         <p>f 95 col 1–f 96 col 1*</p>
         <gap reason="omitted"/>

         <p>The <persName>queen</persName>, who was much delighted, with these Solemnities, was so
            taken with this <name type="entertainment">show &amp; Masque</name>, that she desired to
            see it acted ouer againe, wheruppon, an intimation being giuen to the <persName>Lord
               Maior of <placeName>London</placeName></persName>, he inuited the
               <persName>King</persName> &amp; <persName>Queen</persName> &amp; the <orgName>Innes
               of Court</orgName>
            <persName>Masquers</persName>, to the <placeName>Citty</placeName>, &amp; intertained
            them, with all state &amp; magnificence, att <placeName>Marchant Taylors
               Hall</placeName>.</p>

         <p>Thither marched, through the Citty, the same show, that went before to
               <placeName>Whitehall</placeName>, &amp; the same <name type="entertainment"
               >Masque</name> was againe presented to them in the <placeName>Citty</placeName>, the
            same, <name type="object">horsemen, lacquays, liueries, torches, habits,
            chariots</name>, musicke &amp; all other parts of the<note type="foot"><hi rend="italic"
                  >start of col 2 on f 95</hi></note> former solemnity, &amp; in the same state
            &amp; Equipage as it was before presented.</p>

         <p>This also gaue great contentm<ex>en</ex>t to their
               <persName>M<ex>aies</ex>tyes</persName>, &amp; no lesse to the Cittizens, especially
            to those of the younger sort, &amp; of the female sexe, &amp; it was to the great
            honour, &amp; no lesse charge of the <persName>L<ex>ord</ex> Maior
            freeman</persName>.</p>

         <p>After these dreames past, &amp; these pompes vanished, the Committee of the Masque,
            required an account, of all the disbursements, &amp; all men were satisfyed justly &amp;
            bountifully.</p>

         <p>For the musicke, which was perticularly committed to my charge, I gaue to <persName>Mr
               Iues</persName>, &amp; to <persName>Mr Lawes</persName> 100 l. a piece, for their
            rewards, for the 4 french gentlemen, the Queens seruants, I thought that a hansome &amp;
            liberall gratifying of them, would be made knowne to the <persName>Queen</persName>,
            their Mistris, and well taken by her.</p>

         <p>I therfore inuited them one morning, to a Collation att <placeName>St Dunstans
               Tauerne</placeName>, in the great Roome, the Oracle of Apollo, where each of them had
            his plate layd | for him, couered, &amp; the Napkin ty’d, &amp; when they opened their
            plates they found in each of them, forty pieces of gould, of their Masters coyne, for
            the first dish, &amp; they had cause to be much pleased with this surprisall.</p>

         <p>The rest of the <name type="occupation">Musitians</name>, had rewards answearable to
            their parts, &amp; qualities, &amp; the whole charge of the Musicke, came to about one
            thousand pownds.</p>

         <p>The <name type="object">clothes of the Horsemen, &amp; the liueries of their pages and
               lacquays</name>, which were att their owne perticular charge, were reckoned one with
            another att 100 l. a suit, att the least, &amp; one hundred of those suits, to amount
            unto 10000 l.</p>

         <!-- INNS OF COURT 1633-4                    279 -->

         <p>The Charges of all the rest of the <name type="entertainment">Masque</name>, &amp;
            matters belonging to it, were reckoned att as much more, &amp; so the charge of the
            whole <name type="entertainment">Masque</name>, which was borne, by the societies, &amp;
            by the perticular members of it, was accounted to be aboue twenty thousand pownds.</p>

         <p>I was so conuersant with the <name type="occupation">Musitians</name>, &amp; so willing
            to gaine their<note type="foot"><hi rend="italic">start of col 2 on f 95v</hi></note>
            fauour, especially att this time, that I composed an aier my selfe, with the assistance
            of <persName>Mr Iue</persName>, and called it, <persName>Whitelockes</persName> Coranto,
            which being cryed up, was first played publiquely, by the <orgName>Blackefryars
               musicke</orgName>, who were then esteemed the best common Musicke in all
               <placeName>London</placeName>.</p>

         <p>Whensoeuer I came to that house, (as I did sometimes in those dayes<note type="foot"><hi
                  rend="italic">superfluous closing parenthesis</hi></note>) though not often) to
            see a play, the <name type="occupation">Musitians</name> would presently play
               <persName>Whitelockes</persName> Coranto, &amp; it was so often called for, that they
            would haue it played, twice or thrice in an afternoone.</p>

         <p>The <persName>Queen</persName> hearing it, would not be perswaded, that it was made by
            an Englishman, bicause she said, it was fuller of life &amp; spirit then the English
            aiers use to be, butt she honourd the Coranto &amp; the maker of it with <persName>her
                  M<ex>aies</ex>tyes</persName> royall commendation. |</p>

         <p>It grew to that request, that all the Common <name type="occupation">Musitians</name> in
            this Towne, &amp; all ouer the Kingdome, gott the composition of it, &amp; played it
            publiquely in all places, for aboue thirty years after, Butt I had need to make some
            excuse, for spending my time, then, &amp; now about so light a buisnes as this Coranto
            was, I shall giue the reasons of it…</p>

         <gap reason="omitted"/>

         <p>f 97 col 1–f 97v col 1</p>

         <gap reason="omitted"/>

         <p>A little while after the <name type="entertainment">Masque</name> was performed, the
            Committee ordered <persName>Sir Iohn Fynch</persName>, <persName>Mr Gerling</persName>,
               <persName>Mr Hyde</persName> &amp; <persName>Whitelocke</persName>, to attend the
               <persName>King</persName> &amp; <persName>Queen</persName> &amp; in the name of the 4
               <orgName>Innes of Court</orgName>, to returne their humble thankes, for their
                  <persName>M<ex>aies</ex>tyes</persName> gratious acceptance of the tender of their
            seruice in the late <name type="entertainment">Masque</name>.</p>

         <p>They were first brought to the <persName>King</persName>, who gaue to all of them his
            hand to kisse, then <persName>S<ex>i</ex>r Iohn Fynch</persName><note type="foot"><hi
                  rend="italic">start of col 2 on f 97</hi></note>, in the name of the rest spake to
            the <persName>king</persName> to this effect. S<ex>i</ex>r. By commaund of your
                  <persName>M<ex>aies</ex>tyes</persName> most affectionate, and loyall subiects,
            the Readers<note type="foot">R<hi rend="italic">corrected from g</hi></note> &amp;
            gentlemen of the 4 <orgName>Innes of Court</orgName>, we are heer to attend you, with
            their most humble thankes, for your great fauour to them, in your gratious acceptance,
            of the tender of their seruice &amp; affections to your
               <persName>M<ex>aies</ex>ty</persName> in the late <name type="entertainment"
               >Masque</name> presented to you, &amp; for vouchsafing your royall presence att
            it.</p>

         <!-- 280       INNS OF COURT 1633-4 -->

         <p> The <persName>King</persName>, with great affability &amp; pleasingness, answeared him
            presently to this purpose.</p>

         <p><quote>Gentlemen. I pray assure those from whom you come, that we are exceeding well
               pleased with that testimony which they lately gaue us, of their great respect &amp;
               affection to us, which was very acceptable &amp; performed with that gallantry, &amp;
               in so excellent a manner, that I cannot butt giue them thankes for it, &amp; shall be
               ready upon all occasions to manifest the good opinion | I haue of them, &amp; to doe
               them &amp; you in perticular, any fauour.</quote></p>

         <p>from the <persName>King</persName>, we were brought to the <persName>Queen</persName>,
            &amp; kissed her hand, &amp; <persName>S<ex>i</ex>r Iohn Fynch</persName> her Atturney
            hauing made the like complement to her <persName>M<ex>aies</ex>ty</persName>, she
            answeared, quicke, &amp; well pleased.</p>

         <p>That she neuer sawe any <name type="entertainment">Masque</name> more noble, nor better
            performed then this was, which she tooke as a perticular respect to her selfe, as well
            as to the <persName>King</persName>, her husband, &amp; desired that her thankes might
            be returned to the Gentlemen for it.</p>

         <p>This being reported to the Benchers, of each society, they gaue thankes to their
            respective members, that were of the Committee, for the honour they had done to the
            society, by the well ordering of that buisness of the <name type="entertainment"
               >Masque</name>.</p>

         <gap reason="omitted"/>

         <p><title><hi rend="Bold">Orders of the Committees</hi></title>
            <placeName>Longleat House</placeName>: Longleat MSS Parcel 2, Number 9, item 1</p>

         <p>ff [1–1v]*</p>
         <list>

            <item>All the Committees to be att the place from whence they ride att two a clock and
               there to stay till all the traine bee past the care to be divided amongst them by a
               meeting before</item>
            <item>All the gentlemen that rode to sett downe where they had their horses and saddles
               and to have notice to provide against the time, These Committees to take care of
               it</item>
         </list>

         <!--Mr Brereton    } for Grayes Inne Mr Rutter Mr Gurling  } for lincolns Inne Mr Stile Mr Whitelock } for the middle Temple Mr Hide Mr Cæsar      } for the Inner Temple Mr Pollard-->
         <p>Of every house some to take care for the <name type="occupation">Marshells men</name>
            &amp; <name type="occupation">Torchbearers</name>, to see who have habitts and who
            no</p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
